Now let's talk about Amazon Neptune.
Giờ hãy nói về Amazon Neptune.
Neptune is a fully managed graph database.
Neptune là graph database được quản lý toàn phần.
So an example of what a graph dataset would be
Ví dụ về graph dataset
would be, for example, something we all know,
là thứ mà chúng ta đều biết,
which is a social network.
chính là mạng xã hội.
So if we look at a social network, people are friends,
Trong mạng xã hội, mọi người là bạn,
they like, they connect, they read, they comment, and so on.
họ like, kết nối, đọc, bình luận, v.v.
So users have friends, posts will have comments,
Người dùng có bạn bè, bài viết có bình luận,
comments have likes from users, users share and like posts.
bình luận được người dùng like, người dùng chia sẻ và like bài viết.
And so all these things are interconnected,
Tất cả những thứ đó liên kết với nhau
and so they create a graph.
tạo thành một graph.
And so this is why Neptune is a great choice of database
Vì vậy Neptune là lựa chọn tuyệt vời
when it comes to graph datasets.
cho các graph dataset.
So Neptune has replication across 3 AZ,
Neptune nhân bản dữ liệu trên 3 AZ
up to 15 read replicas.
với tối đa 15 read replica.
It's used to build and run applications that are gonna be
Neptune dùng để xây dựng và chạy ứng dụng
with highly connected datasets, so like a social network,
với dữ liệu liên kết cao, như mạng xã hội,
and because Neptune is optimized to run queries
và vì Neptune tối ưu cho truy vấn
that are complex and hard on top of these graph datasets.
phức tạp trên các graph dataset này.
You can store up to billions of relations on the database
Bạn có thể lưu hàng tỷ quan hệ trong cơ sở dữ liệu
and query the graph with milliseconds latency.
và truy vấn với độ trễ mili giây.
It's highly available with application
Neptune có tính sẵn sàng cao
across multiple availability zones,
trên nhiều availability zone,
and it's also great for storing knowledge graphs.
và cũng rất tốt để lưu knowledge graph.
For example, the Wikipedia database is a knowledge graph
Ví dụ, cơ sở dữ liệu Wikipedia là một knowledge graph
because all the Wikipedia articles are interconnected
vì các bài viết Wikipedia liên kết với nhau
with each other.
.
Fraud detection, recommendations engine,
Các trường hợp sử dụng: phát hiện gian lận, hệ thống gợi ý,
and social networking.
và mạng xã hội.
So coming from an exam perspective,
Từ góc độ kỳ thi,
any time you see anything related to graph databases,
hễ thấy nội dung liên quan graph database
think no more than Neptune.
hãy nghĩ ngay đến Neptune.
Now Amazon Neptune also has a feature
Amazon Neptune còn có tính năng
called Neptune Streams.
gọi là Neptune Streams.
So streams in Amazon Neptune are going
Streams trong Amazon Neptune sẽ
to be a real time ordered sequence of data for every change
là chuỗi dữ liệu theo thứ tự thời gian cho mọi thay đổi
that happens within your graph data
diễn ra trong graph data
in your Neptune database.
trong cơ sở dữ liệu Neptune.
So that means that whenever an application is writing
Điều đó nghĩa là bất cứ khi nào ứng dụng ghi
to Amazon Neptune,
vào Amazon Neptune,
then the changes will be available immediately
thì các thay đổi sẽ xuất hiện ngay lập tức
after writing into that Neptune streams.
sau khi ghi vào Neptune stream.
So in that stream, you have no duplicates
Trong stream đó không có bản ghi trùng
and a strict ordering of changes happening
và thứ tự thay đổi được bảo đảm
within your Neptune cluster.
trong Neptune cluster.
So in a graph, we have rights,
Trong graph, chúng ta có các ghi,
and these rights are written, of course,
và những ghi này được ghi
to your Neptune cluster, but also to a Neptune stream.
vào Neptune cluster và cả Neptune stream.
Now this stream data is accessible using an HTTP REST API.
Dữ liệu stream có thể truy cập qua HTTP REST API.
That means that your applications, for example,
Điều đó nghĩa là ứng dụng của bạn
that want to read your Neptune Stream,
nếu muốn đọc Neptune stream
can use this API to get all the changes in real time.
có thể dùng API này để lấy mọi thay đổi theo thời gian thực.
So the use cases for enabling Neptune streams are,
Các trường hợp sử dụng Neptune streams gồm
for example, to send notifications
gửi thông báo
whenever some changes are made within your graph data,
khi có thay đổi trong graph data,
or to maintain your data synchronized
hoặc đồng bộ dữ liệu
into another data store.
sang một data store khác.
For example, you want to replicate the changes happening
Ví dụ bạn muốn sao chép các thay đổi
within your Neptune cluster into Amazon S3 or OpenSearch
trong Neptune cluster sang Amazon S3 hoặc OpenSearch
or ElastiCache or more.
hoặc ElastiCache hay các dịch vụ khác.
Or if you want to replicate data across multiple regions
Hoặc nếu muốn sao chép dữ liệu giữa nhiều region
for your Neptune cluster by looking at all the changes
cho Neptune cluster bằng cách xem mọi thay đổi
in the stream and rewriting those
trong stream và ghi lại
into a target Neptune cluster.
vào Neptune cluster đích.
Okay, so that's it for this lecture.
Được rồi, bài học đến đây.
I hope you liked it, and I will see you in the next lecture.
Hy vọng bạn thích và hẹn gặp lại ở bài giảng tiếp theo.